PO BOX 49378-00100 NAIROBI +254 701 814701/+254 775 254092

https:/www.linkedin.com/in/manasseh-oduor-03742a11a manassehoduor6@gmail.com/m.datascientist@gmail.com

## AUMA MANASSEH ODUOR

#### **OBJECTIVE**

An entry-level data scientist who takes pride in building models that translate data points into business insights. I have 3+ years of experience in project work and freelance jobs. I participate in data science competition in analytics Vidhya and Kaggle by building models that fit the problem best. Skilled in data mining, machine learning, statistics, problem solving, and programming.

# PERSONAL INFORMATION

NATIONALITY: Kenyan D.O.B: 29-09-1994 GENDER: Male

#### **SKILLS**

- Data Analysis, major tools skills are R-Programming, SPSS, STATA, XLSTAT, and Python.
- Creating data Entry templates using CSPro tool.
- Data Collection management and data compilation.
- Communication, collaboration, problem solving, active learning, perceptiveness, generating hypotheses, judgement, interpersonal skills, creative and critical thinking.
- Report writing.
- Field supervision and coordination.
- Data Munging using R programming language.
- Scripting questionnaire using Survey to go and Survey Monkey.
- Data Visualization skills using Tableau, Power BI, Matplotlib, and Plotly.
- Designing customized dashboards using R-Shiny.
- Database Management Using Oracle and SQL.
- Data Mining and Machine Learning.
- Data centric.
- Statistics, Quantitative Analysis, and Modeling.



#### **ABILITIES**

DATA COLLECTION, DATA ENTRY, DESIGNING QUESTIONNAIRE TEMPLATES, MUNGING DATA, DESIGNING CUSTOMIZED DASHBOARD, ANALYSIS OF DATA BOTH QUALITATIVE AND QUANTITATIVE RESEARCH.

## WORKING EXPERIENCE

#### FREELANCE DATA SCIENTIST.

Fiverr, Guru, and Upwork

NOVEMBER 2017 - PRESENT.

#### **DUTIES & ACHIEVEMTENTS:**

- Worked directly and collaborate with worldwide clients on diverse programming projects.
- Designed customized dashboards using R-Shiny to story tell the process of presenting data in effective visualizations that depict the whole narrative of key performance indicators, business strategies, and processes.
- Analyzed and mashed-up massive amounts of health data to mine useful insights applying the following statistical steps (Problem framing, data understanding, data cleaning, data selection, data preparation, model evaluation, model configuration, model classification/prediction on testing data, model selection, and model deployment).
- Completed a senior project to predict Airbnb house prices and providing insights of the types of properties that generated the greatest return on investment. Used decision trees, SVM, and regression models.
- Used Weka data-mining software to extract informative data patterns by applying supervised and un-supervised algorithms such as J-48, Naïve Bayes, Random Tree, Random Forest, PART, Logistic regression, KNN, SVM, K-Means, and Decision tables in classification, regression and cluster analysis problems. For example, classification algorithms were applied on Web Traffic for detecting DDoS Attack.
- Used R programming language and Weka data-mining software to extract informative data patterns by applying supervised and unsupervised algorithms in chronic disease patients' recommendation system, which helped chronic disease patients to select suitable food product for their health case.

#### Manasseh Oduor

- Used R programming language for exploratory data analysis, which provided excellent visual information on health-related data projects.
- Prepared visually informative dashboards and reports on health-related case study using Power Business Intelligence tool.
- Performed web scraping using r-vest package and conducted sentiment analysis of Amazon Reviews to inform client of the best goods to purchase.
- Scrapped Twitter data using predictive analytics approach in R and Python to detect cyberbullying "Hotspots".
- Conducted Spatial Analysis in R to identify locations "hot spot" in United Kingdom (UK) where most rampant crimes occur.



## JUNIOR DATA SCIENTIST. KAVA AFRICA.

STATION: NAIROBI COUNTY - KILELESHWA.

SEPTEMBER - NOVEMBER 2017.

#### **DUTIES & ACHIEVEMTENTS:**

- Worked directly and collaborate with the Credit Team to understand the performance, risk, and financial impact of our data science models on the portfolio, iterating the model to include new information, data and feedback from various sources.
- Monitored model performance once deployed and recommended rapid iteration if necessary.
- Contributed and shared findings and knowledge of credit risk modeling with all appropriate cross-functional teams.
- Pulled data from MySQL and Metabase, handled all the ETL from the DB to running the model to obtaining a decision.
- Developed and implemented data analytics capabilities both on structured and unstructured data.
- Established and implemented data munging, de-dup, lineage and interrelationship tools and techniques to ensure better use of data.
- Summarized analysis finding and present them during meetings.
- Developed, tested and implemented machine-learning algorithms to solve credit risk problems.
- Developed, deployed and maintain credit-based models by integrating new data sources in our existing underwriting models.
- Prepared visually informative dashboards and reports using Data analytics business intelligence server - Metabase.

#### INTERN.

#### RESEARCH SOLUTIONS AFRICA.

STATION: NAIROBI COUNTY - WESTLANDS.

MAY 2016 - JANUARY 2017.

#### **DUTIES & ACHIEVEMTENTS:**

- Performed Data mining, Web scrapping and storage of data in Mongo database of retail data.
- Collated, Queried and cleaned data coming in from the fields sites including flagging out inconsistencies and/ or errors arising from data obtained from the field as part of routine data checks.
- Performed various data manipulations, analysis and generated reports and tables as required.
- Performed Data Munging and transformation of unstructured retail data using MS Excel and Mongo DB.
- Performed Data Visualization using Power BI and Tableau. Gaining meaningful insights of retail data that helped in data analysis.
- Worked with other team members on various tasks as requested.
- Performed additional responsibilities that were assigned by the supervisor.
- Performed Spatial Analysis. Creating location profile, digitizing bio-food data to a digital map and built beautiful maps of retail data using Q-GIS and Map-Box across Kenya.
- Performed Proximity Analysis of retail data using j-query.
- Built reports on day to day progress on the on-going involved projects and reporting to Research Co-Coordinator.
- Analyzed Structured data using both R and SPSS. Built predictive models using regression algorithms.
- Created Questionnaire templates using Survey To Go. Assisted in scripting Questionnaires for data collection and processing.
- Cleaned and Processed data from field work using SPSS.
- Generated meaningful custom tables as part of the data processing.

#### ATTACHEE'

#### KENYA NATIONAL BUREAU OF STATISTICS.

STATION-KAJIADO COUNTY.

MAY 2015 - AUGUST 2015.

#### **DUTIES & ACHIEVEMENTS:**

- Assisted in Data collection in Kenya Demographic Health Survey.
- Performed data entry processes of registered businesses in Kajiado County using Microsoft Excel.
- Performed calculations of Population projection for Kajiado County.
- Filed of KNBS Statistics documents i.e., Data collected from the field.
- Performed data entry for the post enumeration survey forms using CSPro software.
- Compiled and analyzed data using Microsoft Excel.

#### **EDUCATION**

**Up to Date:** 

2013 - 2019

**KENYATTA UNIVERSITY** 

Second Class Honors in BSc. STATISTICS & PROGRAMMING.

2009 - 2012

KEERU HIGH SCHOOL

KCSE CERTIFICATE, B- (58).

2007-2008

MATHARE NORTH PRIMARY SCHOOL KCPE CERTIFICATE CLASS, C (270) Marks.

2001-2006

SALAMA PRIMARY SCHOOL



### **LANGUAGES**

Language	Read	Write	Speak
AMERICAN ENGLISH	Native	Native	Native
SWAHILI	Native	Native	Native
GERMAN	Beginner	Beginner	Beginner

# COMPUTER APPLICATIONS

		INTER-	
SOFTWARE/PROGRAM	BASIC	MEDIATE	ADVANCED
R-PROGRAMMING/QUANTITATIVE RESEARCH			√
NVIVO/ QUALITATIVE RESEARCH			$\sqrt{}$
SPSS			$\checkmark$
STATA		$\sqrt{}$	
SURVEY MONKEY/ SURVEY TO GO		$\sqrt{}$	
POWER BI/ PLOTLY		$\sqrt{}$	
TABLEAU			$\checkmark$
SQL/ORACLE		$\sqrt{}$	
KNIME			$\sqrt{}$
ORACLE	$\sqrt{}$		
PYTHON		$\sqrt{}$	
MS WORD/ EXCEL/ POWERPOINT			$\sqrt{}$
VB EXCEL/ VISION EXCEL		$\sqrt{}$	
AZURE MACHINE LEARNING STUDIO		$\sqrt{}$	
Q-GIS/MAPBOX	$\sqrt{}$		
CSPRO		$\sqrt{}$	

**COMMUNICATION** Did presentations during the piloting survey review meetings we held regularly to report on progress of work done, areas of difficulties, as well as what I had done to solve issues that arose.

#### **LEADERSHIP**

In the Monthly Consumer Price Index Survey, had the privilege in taking the lead in performance of duties assigned to me by the supervisor and ensuring proper communication of decisions.

# INTERESTS & HOBBIES

- Reading. Currently reading Advanced R- Data Programming and the Cloud
- Data Hobbyist. In my free time, I participate in Online competition, learning platforms and workshops in *Analytics* Vidya, Data Camp and Kaggle.
- Travelling.
- Cooking.
- Playing Rugby. Currently a member of KCB Rugby team, participating in Kenya Cup championship & Eric Shirley Shield.

#### **ATTACHMENTS**

- Kenya Certificate of Primary Education (KCPE).
- Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (KCSE).
- Certificate of Participation for attending and actively participating in a career talk on the Role of Statistics and Actuarial Science in the Corporate World.
- Certificate of learning Data Science from Data Camp.
- Certificate of Bachelor Degree in Statistics and Programming.

# SEMINARS, MEET- UPS AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED

- **Webinar, R & Python, a Love Story.** Key Interest Integration of R-Studio Server Pro with Jupyter Notebooks on a single server January 16, 2020.
- Data Science & Deep Learning Demystified. Intel. Kenyatta University – Friday, May 5th, 2017.
- Introduction to R An Applied approach (1st session) for Data Science. Lynk Office, Nairobi, Kenya – Saturday, April 22nd, 2017.

- Big Data Developers in Nairobi. Machine Learning Launch Livestream - Wednesday, February 15<sup>th</sup>, 2017.
- Data Science Webinar 4. Data Visualization. Web Conferencing Meeting - Tuesday, 11th October 2016.
- Refunite Tech Talks. Storying substantial amounts of user data efficiently. Nairobi Garage, Westlands, Nairobi. Thursday, August 18th, 2016.
- Africa Open Data. East Africa Open Data Festival. August 17<sup>th</sup>-18<sup>th</sup> 2016. Strathmore University Nairobi, Kenya.
- Data Science Webinar 2. Statistical Methods for Data
   Science. Web Conferencing Meeting 16<sup>th</sup> August 2016.
- Monthly Python Meetup. Dynamic Debugging, Jumo world and Moringa School, Reliable Towers, Westlands, Nairobi, Kenya – Thursday, July28th 2016.

#### **REFERENCES**

STATISTICIAN ZACHARY OCHOLA.

NATIONAL SAMPLE SURVEYS & EVALUATION PROGRAM (NASSEP)
DIRECTORATE OF POPULATION AND SOCIAL STATISTICS

KENYA NATIONAL BUREAU OF STATISTICS

TEL-+254 727-819490

Email: zacharyochola@yahoo.com

PIUS NG'ANG'A - COUNTY STATISTICS OFFICER.

KENYA NATIONAL BUREAU OF STATISTICS

KAJIADO COUNTY.

TEL-+254-720-048575

Email - pmnganga@knbs.or.ke, piusmiri@gmail.com

KENNEDY OCHIENG.

SCRIPTING EXECUTIVE

DALBERG RESEARCH

TEL-+254 702579784



Manasseh Oduor Email - kedyochieng@gmail.com

